<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The independency of England endeavored to be maintained by Henry Marten, a member of the Parliament there, against the claim of the Scottish Commissioners, in their late ansvver upon the bills and propostions sent to the King in the Isle of Wight.</title>
            <author>Marten, Henry, 1602-1680.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1648</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 38 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A89606</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M822</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E422_16</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R754</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99873149</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99873149</idno>
            <idno type="VID">161388</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A89606)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 161388)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 66:E422[16])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The independency of England endeavored to be maintained by Henry Marten, a member of the Parliament there, against the claim of the Scottish Commissioners, in their late ansvver upon the bills and propostions sent to the King in the Isle of Wight.</title>
                  <author>Marten, Henry, 1602-1680.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>28 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Peter Cole, at the Printing-Press in Cornhil, near the Royal-Exchange, and John Sweeting, at the Angel in Popes-head Alley,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1648.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Jan: 11th 1647"; the "8" in the imprint has been crossed out.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Scotland. --  Parliament.</term>
               <term>Solemn League and Covenant (1643) --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>England --  Foreign relations --  Scotland --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Scotland --  Foreign relations --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:161388:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE INDEPENDENCY OF ENGLAND Endeavored to be maintained By <hi>HENRY MARTEN,</hi> a Member of the Parliament there, Againſt the Claim of The <hi>SCOTTISH</hi> Commiſsioners, In their late ANSWER UPON THE Bills and Propoſitions SENT to the KING in the Iſle of <hi>Wight.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Peter Cole,</hi> at the Printing-Preſs in Cornhil, near the Royal-Exchange, and <hi>John Sweeting,</hi> at the Angel in Popes-head Alley. 1648.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:161388:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:161388:2"/>
            <head>THE INDEPENDENCY OF ENGLAND Endeavored to be maintained againſt the Claim of the Scottiſh Commiſsioners.</head>
            <p>TO rectifie, not to upbraid you: You have for divers years together been very well entreated by us of this Nation, and that from a willingleſs we ever had, as upon all occaſions, ſo particularly in your per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons; to manifeſt the brotherly reſpect we bear towards them who ſent you: Upon the ſame ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt many former Boldneſſes and Provocations of yours have been winked at by the Parliament, as (I am confident) this laſt Anſwer would likewiſe be, did you not therein ſeem to have remained here ſo long, as to have quite forgotten why you came.</p>
            <p>You may therefore pleaſe to be remembred. That
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:161388:3"/>it was no part of your firſt buſineſs (whatever ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plemental Commiſſions may ſince have been pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured for a further exerciſe of your patience among us) to ſettle Religion, not to make a Peace in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi> ſo as all thoſe devout-like and amicable En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavors for which you think to be thanked, were not onely Intruſions into Matters unconcerning you, but ſo many Diverſions from performing, as you ought what was properly committed to you.</p>
            <p>As for our Religion, ſince the zeal of your Countreymen would needs carry their care thereof ſo far from home, me thinks their Divines, now ſitting with ours at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> might excuſe your trouble in this particular, or at leaſt might teach you by their practice, That your Advice therein to the Parliament is to be but an Advice, and that an humble one.</p>
            <p>As for the other particular of Peace, it is true, that about three years agone here were Ambaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadors from our Neighbors of the <hi>Low-Countreys,</hi> who having found the King almoſt weary of Fight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, made uſe of their Priviledge, and did his Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rand (in ſtead of their Maſters) which was with big words to beg a Peace.</p>
            <p>After that, when the Kings Cauſe had nothing left to lean upon, but the Treachery of our falſe Friends and Servants, an Ambaſſador from our Neighbors of <hi>France</hi> did (<hi>en paſſant</hi>) make a certain overture of Accord betwixt the Crown and the Head. But your employment here from our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bors
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:161388:3"/>of <hi>Scotland</hi> had ſo little relation to Peace, that your onely work was to joyn Counſels with a Committee of ours, in ordering and diſpoſing ſuch. Auxiliary Forces as that Kingdom ſhould ſend into this for carrying on the War.</p>
            <p>As to the Delays you charge upon the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, in that they Anſwer your Papers ſometimes late; and ſometimes not at all, yet require peremptory and ſpeedy Reſolutions from you, as if their dealings were unequal towards you, I hope you will give over making ſuch Conſtructions, when you ſhall conſider how much more buſineſs lies upon their hands, then upon yours; and how much flower progreſs the ſame Affairs muſt needs finde, in paſſing both Houſes, then if they were to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patched onely by four or five Commiſſioners. Were not I conſcious to this truth, and to the abundant civility they have always for you in their undelayed reading, preſent referring, and deſire of complying with what you ſend them, ſo far as might conſiſt with their Duty to this Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, and that they want nothing but time to ſay ſo, I ſhould never have preſumed to truſt ſo great a Cauſe upon the Patronage of ſo rude a Pen: Neither indeed is it left there, my deſign being to let the world imagine, how ſtrong a ſtream of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice runs on our ſide, when I dare oppoſe the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of my ſingle barque, againſt all the advantages of Number, Abilicies, and Countenance that you can meet me with.</p>
            <p>For orders ſake, I ſhall take the pains to ſet the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:161388:4"/>body of your Diſcourſe as upright as I may (its prolixity and perplexity conſidered) upon two feet.</p>
            <p>One is, <hi>The Claim you make in behalf of the Kingdom of</hi> Scotland, <hi>to the inſpection of and conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in the matter of our Laws, and the conditions of our Peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The other (miſtaking the firſt for evinced) is, <hi>Your telling us what you think fit, and what unfit, for us to eſtabliſh in our Church and State, and what way you conceive moſt proper for obtaining of a Peace betwixt the King and us; together with the Proofs wherewith you ſeek to fortifie your ſeveral Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It would give your firſt foot too much ground, to hold Diſpure with you upon the ſecond; therefore ſince a man may ſee by your forward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in printing and publiſhing both theſe and other your Tranſactions with the Houſes, that your Arguments (like the Kings in His Meſſages) are not framed ſo much to ſatisfie the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as to beget in the People a diſ-ſatisfaction towards the Parliament. I will (God enabling me) take a time apart to undeceive my Countreymen concerning both the King and you, by laying the Hook as open as the Bait in all your lines; And for the preſent apply my ſelf onely to the ſhewing you, That when you ſhall have offered your Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel to the Parliament of <hi>England</hi> (as for ought I know any one man may do unto another) in matters concerning this Kingdom onely, though
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:161388:4"/>the moſt wholſom Counſel that ever was or can be given, and the Parliament ſhall not approve it, not ſo much as a Conference upon it, it is no more maners in you, then it would be in the ſame number of Spaniards, Indians, or of the moſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote Region of the Earth, to preſs it again, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt upon it, and to proclaim your unſatisfaction in it.</p>
            <p>Let us (with your favor) confider your pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences: <hi>You do not aym</hi> (as your ſelves profeſs in the ſecond Paragraff of your fourth page) <hi>at ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring in our Rights, Laws nor Liberties, but in other Matters,</hi> viz. <hi>ſuch as either in their own Nature, or by Compact, are common to both King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms;</hi> which I take the more notice of, becauſe one would ſuppoſe you to be grown kinder now then you were the other day, when you went about to make us believe, that nothing in our Laws did properly belong to us, but the form and maner of proceeding therein, the matter of them being held in common with the Kingdom of <hi>Scotland;</hi> and therefore, and for their poſſibility of containing ſomething prejudicial to that Kingdom, to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed by you before they receive their perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
            <p>But the truth is, you are ſtill where you were; onely the Peoples ears are by this time ſo habitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated to the Doctrines you frequently ſow among them, thoſe Doctrines ſo improved by your Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minaties, who finde their own Intereſt interwoven with yours, and the Parliament ſeeming but a
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:161388:5"/>looker on, that you perſwade your ſelves any thing will paſs that you ſhall ſet your Stamp on, otherwiſe you would certainly have been aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to diſavow the buſying your ſelves with our <hi>RIGHTS, LAWS</hi> and <hi>LIBERTIES,</hi> and with the ſame breath to diſpute our Rights, correct our Laws, and infringe our Liberties.</p>
            <p>Nay, contrary to that moderate conceſſion of yours, you do in this Anſwer intrench upon the very form and maner of our Bills and Propoſitions; and as if the marſhalling them, the putting them into rank and file, were to be by your order, you take upon you to appoint which of our Deſires ſhall have the Van, and which the Rere in this Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedition.</p>
            <p>And (which is the moſt pleaſant part of the Story, if it would take, as truly ſuch a thing might have done, when you and we were firſt acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) though the Parliament of <hi>England</hi> (as I told you even now) would not order the motions of the Scottiſh Army that ſerved us in our Countrey, and for our Pay, but by Conjunction of Counſels with Commiſſioners of that Kingdom; yet you (as you could not forbear medling with our Army when it was in modelling, ſo) do in this Paper con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue the Office (you put your ſelves into) of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing, Disbanding, Diſmembring, Catechizing and Reviling this Army of ours, the greateſt Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wark, under God, of our Liberties, that yet had proved ineffectual, if your Counſels had been followed, or your Importunities regarded.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:161388:5"/>
            <p>Since then your way of adviſing us is not in a modeſt or ſubmitting manner, but as if you meant to pinne your advice upon us whether we will or no; give me leave, I pray you, to examine <hi>quâ fiduciâ,</hi> promiſing you faithfully for my part, that whenſoeever you ſhall bring the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters conteſted for, within the rules of your own ſetting downe, that is, <hi>either in nature, or by Covenant, or by Treaty to be of a mixed con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernment;</hi> I will either not deny you <hi>a joynt intereſt</hi> in them, or acknowledge my ſelfe to have <hi>no</hi> more <hi>honour nor conſcience</hi> in mee, then he may be ſaid to have, who being en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſted for his Countrey, gives up their deareſt Rights to the next ſtranger that demands them without ſo much as arguing the point.</p>
            <p>Your arguments (by my computation) are five, and (if I underſtand them) ſpeak thus.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arg.</hi> 1. <hi>The ſame common intereſt upon which</hi> Scotland <hi>was invited and engaged in the warre ought to be [continued]</hi> (ſo I read you, and not improved, that being a wilde expreſſion, and reaching neither you nor I know whether) <hi>in making the peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For anſwer thereunto, ſhould I admit it, the word <hi>[invited]</hi> puts you in minde that your Countrey-men came not to the warre before they were called, keep you the ſame method in <hi>accedendo ad conſilium,</hi> and we ſhall ſtill be friends. But I cannot ſubſcribe to this poſition, for I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve it was a duty that the people of <hi>Scotland</hi> did owne unto themſelvs to give us their aſſiſtance
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:161388:6"/>in the late warre, though they had not been invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; yet doth it not follow from thence that when the warre is ended (as you often ſay it is, and yet moſt riddlingly take huge paynes for Peace) they are bound to mingle with us in our Councels, nor help us to ſettle our own King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, which we thinke our ſelves able to ſettle well enough without them, at leaſt without their prejudice to whom a good Peace or a bad, ſo as it be a Peace is the ſame thing. For inſtance, the Law of this Land that gives me leave to pull down my neighbours houſe when it is on fire, in order to the quenching of it for the ſecuring of my own, will not authorize me againſt his will, to ſet my foot within his threſhold, when the fire is out, though I make it my errand to direct him in the rebuilding of his houſe, and pretend the teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him ſo to contrive his Chimneyes as may in all probability prevent for the future a like loſſe to him, a like danger to my ſelfe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arg.</hi> 2. You demand the ſame conjunction of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts to be given you, that was had of you. There I joyne iſſue with you, and profeſſe, that if ever the Parliament of <hi>England</hi> or any autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity derived therefrom did offer to put a finger into the proper affaires of <hi>Scotland,</hi> or into the Government, Civill, Eccleſiaſticall, or Military of that Kingdome, and being once required to deſiſt, did notwithſtanding proſecute their title of adviſing <hi>volentibus nolentibus,</hi> I ſhall readily ſo farre as in me lyes, grant you to have a hand with us in the managing of this Kingdome, and the government thereof.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:161388:6"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Arg.</hi> 3. You affirm that the Covenant entred into betwixt us makes you co-partners with us in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing there mentioned, by which reckoning neither this Nation, nor that of <hi>Scotland</hi> hath a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny right law or liberty which either can properly and diſtinctly call its own, but both intereſts are jumbled together, and the two Kingdomes are not confederate, but incorporated Concerning the Covenant therefore (which my ſelfe, among others conſidering it firſt as well as I could) have taken) I ſhall ſhortly give you my ſence in relation to the point before us.</p>
            <p>Firſt, I do not conceive the parties to that League intended thereby to be everlaſtingly bound each to other, the grounds of ſtriking it being meerly occaſionall for the joyning in a war to ſuppreſſe a common enemy, accordingly we did joyn, the enemy is (if we be wiſe) ſuppreſſed, and the warre (as you ſay) ended, what ſhould the Covenant do, but like an Almanak of the laſt yeer ſhew us rather what we have already done, then what we be now to do.</p>
            <p>Secondly, what would it do, were it renewed and made perpetuall? Thus much it ſaith in my opinion, and no more. Whenſoever you ſhall be violently hindred in the execution of that Religion you had amongſt you at the time of the engagement, and ſhall require our aſſiſtance, we muſt afford it you, for the removall of that vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olence. In like manner, whenſoever we ſhall be ſo hindered in the exerciſe of that Religion which we according to that Covenant ſhall eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:161388:7"/>here, upon requeſt to you made for that effect, you are tyed to aſſiſt us. And ſo throughout all the other clauſes reſpective<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and equally, carrying this along with you; we are hereby obliged to the reciprocall defence of one another according to the Declaration of the party wronged in any of the particulars there compriſed, without being cavilled at, or ſcrupled by the party invoked, whether your Religion be the ſame it was, or ours the ſame it ſhould be, whether the bounds of your liberties or ours be not enlarged beyond their then-line, whether your Delinquents or ours be juſtly ſo or no. For, the native rights of both peoples being the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall, if not the onely thing we looked on, when we ſwore; we do not keep our oath in preſerving thoſe rights, if we do not allow this maſter-right, to each ſeverall people, namely, to be ſole judges within themſelves, what Religion they will ſet up, what kind of Lawes they will have, what ſize, what number of Magiſtrates they hold fit to exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute thoſe Lawes, and what offenders to be tryed by them. Hereupon you know we did not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire at all how Orthodox your Religion was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we vowed to maintain you in it, that is, in the quiet profeſſing of it, (not in the Theologi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call truth of it, a buſineſſe for a Univerſity per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps, not for a Kingdome) being well aſſured, it was eſtabliſhed by them who had all the authority that is viſible to chuſe for themſelves, and could not without apparent breach of order, and injury to fundamentals be diſturbed in the exerciſe of what they had ſo choſen.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:161388:7"/>
            <p>So farre is the plaine text of this Covenant from confounding intereſts that it cleerly ſettles and confirmes them upon the ſeverall baſes where it found them. And it would not be unworthy of you to take heed leſt this Covenant upon which you ſeem to ſet ſo high a rate, be not as eaſily vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated as ſlandered, ſince the moſt deadly warres have been ſaid at leaſt to begin with miſ-under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arg.</hi> 4. Your entituling your ſelvs to a conuſance in the conditions of our Peace, and conſequently in the matter of our Lawes (when they relate to an agreement, as I confeſſe the four Bils do which were ſent) is grounded upon a very great miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take of the eighth article in the treaty, the words whereof are indeed very rightly incited by you, and the article it ſelf ſo rationall, ſo ordinary, ſo neceſſary in all warres joined in by two States, that I do almoſt wonder as much what need there was to have inſerted it, as I do how it is poſſible for you to miſtake it. It ſtands briefly thus. One of you (for the purpoſe) &amp; I (pardon if you pleaſe the familiarity of the inſtance) have ſolemnly enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged our ſelves each to other for our mutuall aid a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt a third perſon, becauſe we conceived him too ſtrong for either of us ſingle, or becauſe one of us doubted he might have drawn the other of us to his party, if not pre-engaged againſt him, but which ſoever of us was firſt in the quarrell, or what ever was the reaſon of the others coming in, we are engaged, &amp; though there were nowritings drawn betwixt us, no terms expreſſed, were not I the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:161388:8"/>verieſt <hi>Schelm</hi> that ever looked man in the face if I ſhould ſhake hands with the common adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and leave you fighting? againſt ſuch a piece of baſenes (ſuppoſing it belike to be in nature) this Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle provides, and ſaies that ſince theſe two King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms were content to joyn in a war which without Gods great mercy might have proved fatall to them both, neither of them ſhall be ſuffered to make its peace apart; ſo as if the Parlianent of <hi>Scotland</hi> upon conſideration of reaſons occurring to themſelves ſhould offer to readmit the King in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to that Kingdom (I ſay not with honour, free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and ſafety but) in peace, the Parliament of <hi>England</hi> might ſtep in and forbid the banes, tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling them we are not ſatisfyed that an agreement ſhould yet be made, <hi>ſimiliter,</hi> if this Parliament would come to any Peace with him by Bills or Propoſitions, or by what other name ſoever they call their plaiſters, you may (being ſo authorized) in name of that Kingdome or the Parliament, thereof intervene, and oppoſe, telling us that you who are our fellow-Chirurgions, meerly in launcing of the ſore, are not ſatisfied in the time for the healing of it up. But for you to read a lecture to us upon our medicaments and their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gredients, to take meaſure of our wounds, and to prefer your meaſure before that of our own ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king was never dreamt on by the Framers of this article.</p>
            <p>Here it may perhaps be demanded though not by you, whether (according to my ſence of the treaty, tying up both Kingdoms to a conſent in the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:161388:8"/>
               <hi>Fiat,</hi> not in the <hi>Qualis fuerit</hi> of Peace) if one ſhould be obſtinately bent to hang off, the other be neceſſitated to welter everlaſtingly in blood for want of ſuch a concurrence. I anſwer, yes, for theſe reaſons.</p>
            <p>Firſt, a wiſe man will fore ſee inconveniences, before he make his bargaine, and an honeſt man will ſtand to his bargaine notwithſtanding all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conveniences.</p>
            <p>Secondly, there will be no great encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for any obſtinacy of that kinde when it ſhall be remembred that the party obſtructing the peace muſt continue to joyne in the warre, and is ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to all the conſequences thereof.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, there is another and a more naturall way to peace and to the ending of a warre then by agreement, namely by conqueſt. I think he that playes out his ſet at Tennis till he win it, makes as ſure an end of it, and more fair, then hee that throwes up his Racket when he wants but a ſtroke of up, having no other way to rook thoſe of their money that bet of his ſide. If I am truſted to follow a ſuit in Law for friends concerned there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, together with my ſelfe, and daube up a rotten compromiſe with my adverſary, my fellowes not conſulted, but deſiring the ſuit ſhould ſtill goe on, it is not fit they ſhould be bound thereby; but if I continue to doe my duty and bring the cauſe to hearing to a verdict thereupon, and to judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon that; ſuch an end of the quarrell I hope I may make without their leave, and if the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:161388:9"/>tryall went with me, certainly without their of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence.</p>
            <p>To returne to the nature of confederacies, Is the warre wherein we are joyned an invaſion from without? any one man of either ſide if he have ſtrength enough, hath authority enough to end it by repelling the invader, is it a rebellion from within? it were ſtrange to think that any Law or engagement ſhould hinder a ſingle man from end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it, if he be able by ſuppreſſing of the rebels. The unworthy friend in the fable, when his compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and he met a bear in the wood, might have been allowed to kill her himſelfe, but he ſhould not have ſought his ſafety in a tree, without ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king his friend along with him.</p>
            <p>One thing more I ſhall adde to juſtifie the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of this 8. Article, ſuch as might (for its clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of being implyed) have excuſed its be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing liſted among the reſt. Never did any peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple that joyned in armes with a neighbour-na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion patch up a peace apart, with more diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to it ſelfe, then either of us ſhould do, if we could imagine our ſelves to be ſo vile; for the common enemy in this warre is not a ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger unto either Kingdome, but the King of both, ſo as which ſoever of the two cloſeth with him by it ſelfe, before conſent, that there ſhall be at all a cloſure, doth not onely with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw from the other thoſe aides it ſhould con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute, but of a ſworne Brother becomes an open enemy.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:161388:9"/>
            <p>Here I muſt obſerve, that as you put an inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation upon this Article, which it wil not bear, and from the power you have thereby of hindering us from agreeing with the King at all, would enable your ſelves to pry into the particulars of our Agreement, ſo you do not once glaunce at the point which was the true genuine ſcope of the Article: You do not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt againſt our making peace with this man; and give ſuch reaſons as <hi>Jehu</hi> did, upon a leſs occaſion: You do not wonder what confidence we can repoſe in him, after all this experience of him, and before ſo much as a promiſe of any amendment from him; you do not warn us, by the example of your Country men, what a broken reed we ſhal lean upon when we make a paci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication with him: You do not remember us with what horror the Aſſembly of your Church did look upon his miſdoings; nor what ſence both Kingdoms had (not of a reconcilement with him, but) of ſuffering him to come neer the <hi>Parliament of England,</hi> until ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction were given <hi>for the blood which he had then cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to be ſhed in the three Kingdoms.</hi> In fine, You do not ſay (for you need not give us your reaſons) that you wil make no peace with the King; therefore we ought not, but you do as bad as ſay that you have made your peace already, and that not only without our conſent (in deſpite of the Article which you urge againſt us) but without our privity, that you are come a degree beyond being friends with him, to be advocates for him, not in mediating that his ſubmiſſion might be accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, his crimes obliterated, and their ſalary remitted, but in aſſerting the ſame cauſe which we have been
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:161388:10"/>all this while confuting with our ſwords, the ſame cauſe, which, what Engliſh-man or Scotiſh-man ſoever ſhal have endeavored to maintain in Arms, is a decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Traytor to his Country, if by his tongue or pen in that Kingdom of the two where he is no Native, a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt incendiary. But there wil be time enough to do your errand into <hi>Scotland</hi> after I have proved <hi>England</hi> to be a Noun Subſtantive, againſt which you have the ſhadow of one Argument left ſtil.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ar.</hi> 5. The ſtrength of your laſt Reaſon is this. Our Parliament hath formerly communicated unto you the matter of their Propoſitions, and of their Bils, in order to Peace, and generally indeed whatever hath paſſed betwixt the King and us, ſince the conjunction of the two Kingdoms againſt him. Thereupon you have offered us your Advice concerning the Particulars ſo communicated, and we have re-conſidered them upon your Advice, ſometimes complying therewith, other times making it appear to you why we could not; that communication of counſels, ſay you, we would never have ſuffered, if we had not been bound to it, which if we ever were, we ſtil are.</p>
            <p>Cuſtom and conſtant uſage (I acknowledg) doth commonly obtain the name of Law: but the late pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of ſome four or five years, hath not an aſpect reverend enough to deſerve the name of Cuſtom; it is as old (you wil ſay) as an uſage can be that is grounded upon a treaty of the ſame age, and ſhal be ſufficient to ſignifie how the parties to the Treaty did underſtand their own meaning. I ſhould not deny this pretence of yours to be more then colourable,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:161388:10"/>if you could prove that our tranſactions with the King were imparted to you in relation to that Engagement, nay if I could not ſhew you upon what other ground we did it, and that we could not reaſonably be imagined to do it upon that.</p>
            <p>Firſt, to prove, what the Parliament had in their inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, when they adviſed with you, I beleeve you wil not undertake, eſpecially this being the firſt time, to my remembrance, that this point came in queſtion betwixt us. I ſhal therefore endeavor to tel you, as neer as I can, (having been an attentive witneſs to moſt of their Debates upon that ſubject) what it was that moved them to give your challenge ſo much probability of advantage as this amounts unto. <hi>You ask that now, without being anſwered, which you were wont to have without asking.</hi> You were ſo; and that from theſe two Roots: One was the extraordinary care the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament had to omit no act, no circumſtance, of civi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity towards you, which might expreſs or preſerve the amity and correſpondence betwixt them and your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, though they were not ignorant what extream prejudice courteous and good natured men have often drawn upon themſelves in their dealing with perſons of a contrary diſpoſition. Another was, ſince both King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms have been imbarqued in the ſame cauſe, as men of War, and were afterwards reſolved to trade for peace, ſince the commodities of both were to be ſtowed in the ſame bottom, and bound for the ſame Port; we thought it but an ordinary piece of friendſhip, for us who could make no markets, when we ſhould be arrived without your allowance to open and let you ſee before we laun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:161388:11"/>our ſeveral parcels and inſtructions concerning what we would export and what bring home; not that we meant to conſult you what kind of Merchandize you thought fitteſt for us to deal in, which queſtionleſs is better known at the <hi>Exchange</hi> then at <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> nor to follow ſuch advice therein as you ſhould give us without asking any further then we liked it; and ſo far the beſt Merchant in <hi>London</hi> is content to be ruled by the Swabber of his ſhip: but meerly to the end, you might (if you pleaſed) from our example, and from your aprobation of the ware we were reſolved to deal in, furniſh that Kingdom (whoſe Factors you were) with Merchandize of the ſame kind, and for evidence that the Freedom we uſed towards you was no other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe underſtood by you, you did actually under write divers of our Bils of Lading in theſe ſillables: <hi>The like for the Kingdom of Scotland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It remains to be ſhewed how litle reaſon there is you ſhould fancy to your ſelves ſuch a ground of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments former openneſs to you, as you ſtrive to father upon them. For, firſt, If they had communicated their Propoſitions to you as conceiving the word <hi>[A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement]</hi> in the eighth Article to comprehend all the preparations to, materials of, and circumſtances in an Agreement, they would not have adhered (as many times they did) unto their own reſolutions notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding your reiterated diſſatisfaction. Again, If they had conceived themſelves bound to any ſuch thing by this Article, would they not have thought the Kingdom of <hi>Scotland</hi> as much bound for their parts; Should we not have been as diligent inſpectors and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtigators
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:161388:11"/>of your Propoſitions as you have made your ſelves of ours?</p>
            <p>When you ſhal ask me, ſetting the point of duty aſide, and granting all that hath bin done by us in this kind to have been voluntary; Why we do not obſerve the ſame forwardnes in communicating our matters to you, the ſame patience in expecting your concurrence with us, and the ſame eaſineſs of admitting your <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rangues</hi> and Diſputations amongſt us, which you have heretofore taſted at our hands, and how we are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come leſs friendly then we were. I have this to ſay. There is ſome alteration in the condition of affairs: So long as we needed the aſſiſtance of your Country<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men in the Field, we might have occaſion to give you meetings at <hi>Derby</hi> Houſe, and now and then in the <hi>Painted Chamber,</hi> it being likely that the Kingdom of <hi>Scotland</hi> might then have a fellow-feeling with us of the wholeſomneſs or perniciouſneſs of your counſels; whereas now ſince we are able (by Gods bleſſing) to protect our ſelves, we may ſurely (with his holy dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction) be ſufficient to teach our ſelves how to go about our own buſineſs, at leaſt without your tutoring, who have nothing in your conſiderations to look upon, but either your particular advantage, or that of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom whence you are. And as there is ſome alteration in affairs, ſo there is very much in perſons, I mean in your ſelves, unleſs being indeed the ſame at firſt which now we find you, you only wanted an opportunity to appear; but whether you be changed or diſcovered, what Engliſh-man ſoever ſhal peruſe the Papers that you have ſhot into both Houſes of Parliament, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially into the Houſe of Commons theſe two laſt years
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:161388:12"/>had as lieve take advice from the King as from you, &amp; if a ſtranger ſhould read them, he would litle ſuſpect the writers for Friends, or Counſellers, but for Pleaders, for Expoſtulators, for Seekers of a quarrel, and that (which is the moſt bitter weed in the pot) in the behalf, not ſo much of them who did employ you, as of him againſt whom you were employed, and againſt whom, if you were Scottiſh-men, nature would teach you to employ your ſelves.</p>
            <p>By this time I hope you ſee we have greater cauſe to repent, that we have kept ſuch thornes thus long in our ſides, then to return with the dog to the ſame vomit, and with the lazy Sow, ſcarce clenſed of herformer wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing to bemire our ſelves again. I beſtow a little the more ink upon this point, becauſe I would prevent the like claim hereafter, and have it left to the liberty of this nation, next time they ſhall be invaded or op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, though they did once call in their Brethren of <hi>Scotland</hi> to their aide, whether they wil do ſo any more or no.</p>
            <p>Having gone through your 5 Arguments, at the end of your dozen Commandements (ſo I call <hi>deſires that muſt not be ſlighted ou pain of incurring the guilt of violating Engagements, and of ſuch dangers as may enſue thereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi>) I obſerve one engine you uſe, whereon you lay more weight then upon all you ſay beſide; It begins with a flouriſh of oratory beſpeaking a fair Interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of your meaning, though your motion be to take the right eye out of every one of our heads; then you think to make your deſires legitimate with fathering them upon a <hi>Kingdom,</hi> and put us in mind how wel that <hi>Kingdom</hi> hath deſerved to raign over this. For to the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:161388:12"/>offering of deſires, as deſires, there needs no merit, ſure, but ſince your opinion, (that the advantages of honor lie all on that ſide, and that Obligations of this ſort have not been as reciprocall between both Nation, as thoſe of Leagues and Treaties,) wil force my pen upon this Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject. I ſhall let you know that ſome what may be ſaid (when modeſty gives leave) on this ſide too; and yet all the kindneſſes we have received from <hi>Scotland,</hi> ſhall (by my conſent) not only be payd for, but acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: and I can be content to beleeve, that our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours did not know how ill we were, till we were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt paſt cure, and therefore came ſlowly to us; that they did not know how wel we were in a year after we had nothing for them to do, and therefore went ſlowly from us. Only I would have it confeſſed, that the fire we talk of, was of your Countrymans kindling, began to burn at your houſe, to be quenched at ours and by our hands. But admit this Nation had been meerly paſſive in this War, and did owe their deliverance out of the Kings Talons wholly to the Scottiſh Nation, if the reſcuer become a raviſher, if they have protected their own prey, they have merited only from them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and have their reward in their hands. What have we gotten by the bargain? What have we ſaved? What have we not loſt? For if once you come to fetch away my Liberty from me, I ſhal not ask you what o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thing you wil leave me: and the Liberty of a peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple governed by Laws conſiſts in living under ſuch Laws as themſelves or thoſe whom they depute for that purpoſe ſhal make choice of: To give out orders is the part of a Commander; to give the Law, of a Conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror;
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:161388:13"/>although our Norman did not think ſit ſo to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe his right of Conqueſt; Nay our condition would be lower and more contemptible, if we ſhould ſuffer you to have your will of us in this particular, then if we had let the King have his.</p>
            <p n="1">1. A King is but one Maſter, and therefore likely to ſit lighter upon our ſhoulders then a whole Kingdom, and if he ſhould grow ſo heavy as cannot wel be born, he may be ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner gotten off then they. You ſhal ſee a Mounſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours horſe go very proudly under a ſingle man, but <note>PLACE="marg" n="*" To carry double</note> to be <hi>Charge en crouppe,</hi> is that which nature made a mule for, if nature made a mule at all.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The King never pretended to the framing and impoſing of Laws upon us as you do; he would have been content with ſuch a negative voyce therein, as we allow you in the making of our peace with him; did we fight rather then afford him ſo much, though ſeemingly
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:161388:13"/>derived unto him from his Predeceſſors; and ſhal we tamely give you more? Give you that which your Anceſtors never yet durſt ask of ours?</p>
            <p n="3">3. Laſtly, it had been far more tolerable for the King, then for any Forraign Nation to have a ſhare in the making of our Laws, becauſe he was likely to partake, and that largely in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of them, if good; in the inconveniences, if bad; which ſtrangers are not: nay contrarily, it is matter of envy and jealouſie betwixt neighbours to ſee each other in a flouriſhing eſtate. So as the proper end of Laws, being to advance the people, for whom they are made in wealth and ſtrength, to the uttermoſt; they are the moſt incompetent Judges of thoſe Laws in the world, whoſe intereſt it is to hinder that people from growing extreamly rich or ſtrong.</p>
            <p>By what hath been already ſaid, and by a word or two of cloſe, it wil (I hope) appear, that the claim you make to the voting with us in the matter of our Laws, and the conditions of our peace as a thing whereunto we ſhould be obliged by agreement, is;</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:161388:14"/>
            <p n="1">1. Miſtaken in matter of Fact, there being no ſuch engagement on either ſide.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Unreaſonable for the conſiderations above mentioned and for being deſtructive to the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry principles of property.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Unequal (notwithſtanding the reciprocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) more then Cyrus, his childiſh judgment was, in making the little boy change coats with the great one, becauſe his was long and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſhort: For our coats are not only longer then yours, but as fit for us that do wear them, as for you that would.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Unuſual, there being no preſident for it, that I could ever read or hear of; and yet there have been leagues betwixt ſtates of a ſtricter U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:161388:14"/>then this betwixt us, as offenſive and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſive, ours only defenſive.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Unſafe, for the keeping up of hedges, bounda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and diſtinctions (I mean reall and juriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive ones, not perſonal and titulary) is a ſurer way to preſerve peace among neighbours, then the throwing all open. And if every man be not admitted wiſe enough to do his own buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, whoever hath the longeſt ſword will quickly be the wiſeſt man, and diſ-inherit all his neighbours for Fools.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Impoſſible to be made good to you, if it had been agreed: For the Parliament it ſelf, from whom you claim, hath not in my humble opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion authority enough to erect another autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity equal to it ſelf.</p>
            <p>As for your exhortations to piety and loyal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, wherewith you conclude. When you have a mind to offer Sacrifice to your God, and Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:161388:15"/>to your Emperour (ſince the one wil not be mocked, and the other ſhould not) you may do wel to do it of your own, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, that the late unnaturall war with all the Calamities that have enſued thereon, took its riſe from unnaturall enchroachments upon the ſeverall Rights and Liberties of two Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, reſolved it ſeems to hold their own with the hazard of a war, and all the Calamities that can enſue thereon.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Henry Marten.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
